So.
Last week I was attending the
Supercomputing conference.
It was in San Luis.
In the middle of nowhere and it was
interesting anyway.
Uh.
Even though,
as you may have noticed that we got some
problems in Pisa,
so during the day I was attending
meetings and during the night I was
debugging to stay in the network in Pisa
from Monday to Wednesday.
Nevertheless,
it was interesting here and I think that
there are few considerations that are
worth sharing.
Even though it is a conference dedicated
to HPC. OK, how to be supercomputers so.
I attended 15 editions of this conference.
This is the largest conference worldwide.
Of supercomputing.
And of course,
every vision is affected by the hype of
the moment.
So the first thing that you notice is
that now it's like entering a plumber
shop.
That's the feeling you have when you're
entering,
because there is a huge exhibition.
I mean,
you can work one hour just to have a
quick view of all the stands with all the
companies trying to.
To tell how they are redefining the world
and and there are a few things that are
evident first if I.
OK, that's easy. Yeah, I was everywhere.
I was used to implement.
I was optimized to run,
pick up the one you you prefer the most.
By the way, I met Jensen,
the CEO from Nvidia.
Um.
I was there announcing the new things
about the the I of course.
Everyone is scared because there is
clearly a bubble,
a financial bubble around the eye,
because many investors use it.
The AI brand to get money and they will
not produce any value out of them and
eventually.
People will start asking.
Sorry,
let me answer this because I suspect that.
They said that the ministry was looking
for me, so I was.
I thought it was the ministry. Sorry.
It was a user asking.
Uh, so.
The first thing so it is AI and the
bubble will eventually blow up.
It would burn.
Few billions or more billions and and
eventually as it happened probably with
the Internet because around 2000 it was a
similar situation.
Everyone was investing in the in November
anyway actually.
There was a collapse,
but the web is still there.
It's still unimportant technology,
social are important, etcetera.
So I mean that is the overhype.
Sometimes it's just an overhype.
Sometimes there is a technology,
but the enthusiasm brings.
And both too much the the hype.
So the second one is compute power.
OK, so compute power is very, very, very,
very important. Compute power is about.
Um.
Then anticipation.
Those of you that will attend attend the
ACTA infrastructure course will learn
more in the second semester,
but at the same time.
It is only also a problem of efficient
use of the machines.
So a server today easily cost at least 60,
000 EUR. So if I spend 60,000 EUR.
To get a server.
Clearly I'm expecting that that server
will will be used as more as much as
possible to to get some return from the
investment.
And the other big,
big theme is and which is strictly
related to.
To rogramming is power consumption.
So um.
They have these racks with 1000 times on
the back.
There are not not even anymore the cables
because the amount of current is such
that you can't use a cable to bring the
cable. So there is a bar.
And there is a sort of mechanism that
inserts the server in this barring
against the power. OK.
And from our perspective, as programmers,
this means that we will be asked of more
and more efficiency in using, we call it,
we writing and to this respect.
Concurrency is one of the key elements to
get the most out of this.
I had some meetings with the private
meetings.
Actually they showed us the roadmap next
five years.
And uh,
CPUs will get a ridiculous number of
cores.
So there is a there are a lot of problems
of concurrent access to the memory.
OK,
because we're not used to thinking in
these terms, but when you write a program,
this program access to the memory,
you will run on a core inside the CPU.
And let me show you briefly this because
I think it's an interesting.
This is an old CPU.
From.
Oh.
This is a 10 years old project.
Nevertheless.
It's interesting because since then CPUs
have evolved, but not that much.
So they were in many ways, but not.
So when you enter the CPU when you write
a program.
You you tend to think that is a
mathematical abstract entity,
which in part is we spoke about formal
semantics, the meaning of the program. OK,
but eventually this program will become a
sequence of bytes that will be executed.
By the CP and the CP is much more than
what you are using to think.
I mean we have a fairly simple model in
mind, of course.
All these computing elements at the core,
they still use the patches that you cycle,
OK, but they do more.
They do fresh prediction.
So they try to do formal analysis on the
machine language to decide whether you
can cache instructions or not,
because if you branch some cache will
will be flushed and.
Some latency will be introduced.
So this was a 72 course machine.
Nowadays it's pretty common as an
architecture and they probably for the
first time they introduced that.
So every one of these rectangles which is
called a tile.
Is made of two cores.
And they share of course there is a first
level of cache is inside the two cores
and then there is the sort of proxy.
So there is some silicon that is
dedicated to communicate.
In a bidimensional mesh,
so that accessing the the the RAM allows
you.
So if this guy and this guy have to
access this module,
they have different patterns so locks
will not block.
Uh, the.
The the the access to the RAM.
Otherwise you may think that since you've
got the program and the thread you you
you will have to find to access the
memory in fact.
As the number of core has grown and now
stronger match.
Uh.
There's been the need to have a dedicated
memory,
which these days is called HBM high
bandwidth memory to allow the throughput.
That many cores will generate access in
the ramp. OK, so any of anyone of you?
I have an idea of the current.
This is the structure of the core and the
threading and I was hoping to see also
the the tiles. This is the interconnect.
So every tile is the agent that allows
the communication on the bus.
But this is not an architecture course.
So just to give you to introduce the the
point and the fact that when you write a
program,
this program should run on this thing. OK.
And so of course the algorithms matter.
Of course the PROGRAMMING language
matters because.
We said OK, C is faster,
C is C Python is terribly slow and so a
single core will take more time to give
the same computation.
One is best to interpret and the other is
compiled. We discussed also this,
but we risk to get ourselves trapped in
the idea that there is a single CPU which
runs your code and the only.
Not that you have in your mind is to
optimize the algorithm,
which is not and you have to understand.
How this the the the ground under your
feet is like to be able to to choose the
proper shoes and decide whether to run or
whether to get the right performance. OK,
so.
This is an element that you all have to
take into your mind,
because sometimes we tend to think that
the world is made of x86 code,
compilers and that's it,
which is not today.
It it can be X86, it can be this five,
it can be arm.
And even if it's R,
it depends on the architecture.
It's R is an instruction set,
but the implementation depends from
different values.
So is different than or from other state
concept.
So all these elements contribute.
Together with your breathing system.
To tell me the performance of the
programs. OK, so today.
We start.
I don't think we will be able to finish.
We start talking about concurrent
programming.
And as I was saying,
computer PROGRAMMING is a part about
importance because programs will run
either on your phone and I'll be sure
that you're not happy when you install an
application on your phone.
And the button will raise in 5 minutes
and you have to uninstall the application.
Nor an enterprise is happy when spends so
much money in in buying a server and then
it gets as much as a PC because the
program is low. OK, so.
Either way,
program efficiency is crucial and I mean
this is the ADVANCED PROGRAMMING course.
We try to introduce you with all we.
Abstractions that involved in the last
five decades that contributed to define
target PROGRAMMING languages. But please,
please,
please don't forget that these things.
Will run on top of some hardware and you
and on top of operating system and it is
the combination of these things that will
determine the performance and the
behaviour of the application.
So it's naive.
Thinking that the PROGRAMMING language is
a self-contained island and concurrent
PROGRAMMING perhaps has been the first
showing us this.
Concept. OK, briefly.
Let's talk about operating system.
So what what what are the mechanism of
concurrency that the operating system
provides?
Sorry, fork, fork, fork,
which is here too.
To create processes.
So processes where the concurrent unit
until the 90s.
OK. Still, I mean,
they are not only a confulent unit,
they are also a boundary of security and
a boundary of memory.
And so thanks to the visual memory.
Implementation.
You have the ability to run your code as
if the computer was yours,
even though it's not like this. OK,
processes.
Then.
A program is basically what controls a
processor.
So this operating system loads the
program into the memory and then say
process go. This is your program.
OK and then you shut that other forms.
Breads. What are breads?
They are basically a sort of smaller
processes which of course they fight for
the CPU.
So if I look from the CPU perspective,
threats are implemented processes.
But they are not processing water.
The memory is shared,
so basically the context feature only
relates to the registers if you're
switching to a thread of the same process,
otherwise you have to do the food switch.
Then there are others.
These were the easy one.
Mutex are not a form of competency,
are a form of synchronization,
which is very important and we will
discuss later.
This is the first part of this class.
It will be basically a break up.
So that I force you to remember all all
the the piece of the puzzle.
Otherwise it's pointless to discuss about
concurrent PROGRAMMING in PROGRAMMING
languages.
There are.
Uh, so-called collaborative concurrency.
In Windows,
that was implemented in a form of fibers.
Only of them were multiple libraries.
Collaborative concurrency is basically a
software abstraction without the
preaction, OK.
You learned in the operating system that
one core mechanism of the operating
system is to be able to preempt,
so suspend in fact the execution of the
process which is running on a CPU,
save all the.
All the state and then switch one of the
process and this action is imposed on on
the process. Of course,
if the process tries to reach at least
will suspend automatically because it
will wait for the input output operation
to complete.
But if it's CPU only code,
I don't know Monte Carlo simulation,
then this will keep running on and on
unless you interrupt.
Collaborative.
Concurrency is basically a library which
allows you to say it's like a thread,
but you have no way to preempt the
execution.
Is that popular is more available,
especially in no libraries in C.
It was using a lot because it's the
easiest format to implement. Windows 3.
1 was terrible because it didn't have the
pre-emption on the CPU because it was
basically impossible to obtain that at
the time so.
In left.
And of course,
what is the risk that collaborative
concurrency?
If you don't give up spontaneously,
you can block everything.
Advantage is that you get less,
less there is structure involved in
implementation, OK.
So this is basically the panorama of
concurrency.
Help.
Let's take out the process.
The processor is basically.
A domain for the memory for the program,
so typically there is.
One-on-one mapping between the processor.
And the programmer during the execution.
Beware.
You add.
It is true that a program is run by a
process.
Multiple instances of the program,
as we all know,
can be run on multiple process,
but mobile.
Device introduced the weaker connection
between the process and the programmer.
If you remember, we mentioned a bit.
Two weeks ago.
When we're talking about civilization,
because at some point we said, OK,
but we don't want so many processes
running on our mobile because otherwise
the battery will last very little and so.
You know what?
We can somehow save the state of the of
the program, of the process,
kill the process,
and then start another process.
Start the program in that process and say,
OK, this is your state, load it,
keep going.
And.
We were because all these are elements
that are at the complexity and eventually
they found their way into the programming
languages.
In the origin they were not there.
But since it was important.
With time programming,
they start to be including these features
inside the definition and this thing is
important because.
When we define the semantics of a
programming language,
we basically define the semantics of this.
Team 12 machine.
So the semantics of a programming
language is given in terms of a sort of a
virtual machine capable of interpreting
the programmer at the language level. OK,
that is.
And so uh.
This shift in the implementation has
changed the way we we think about
programs.
For a very long time,
programming programs,
programming languages were taught as
mathematical entities,
computing functions. You spend some time,
a lot of time in studying computability.
The program termination and you Lambda
calculus and all these things you know
were rooted in mathematics.
You know what?
When you introduce concurrency,
the program is not anymore determinist.
There are external factors that makes the
program execution unique every time.
We are used to that.
We know that the execution for some part
portion of the execution,
it still is mathematics.
It still is the computation of a function,
but we if we go upstairs,
this is not true anymore.
And that basically introduced a need for
programming languages to introduce
non-mathematical functional objects in
their semantics and in the semantics of
the.
User machine.
Of course,
if you study the theory of Turing
machines, just to mention something.
There are concurrent to the machines,
etcetera. OK,
so there have been attempt to define
abstract machines capable of of
expressing also concurrency. OK,
so I'm not saying.
If possible,
but nevertheless if we look at the
programming language,
this asked to introduce no functional
element in its definition.
Or there is say you don't know I'm
functioning.
You can use external libraries and do
whatever you want,
but I I'm still is I I am still function
OK.
Not without irony. C is on this page,
C says. I mean, I have no threats.
You want to threats,
there are like or you can call the
operating system function,
but I have no threats.
By definition, there are no sets. Yes,
I give you only one spare,
but it's a library.
It's a it's not part of the language,
the ability of saving the state of the
CPU. That's the only exception there.
And then borderline, in fact,
is being used to implement the CMC,
but apart from this.
Uh.
Cooperative threats in C Apart from this,
the first,
the first very large switching produced
concurrence explicitly was.
There's the sorry.
That's me.
Made popular in the maze.
They were ready to grammy languages that
were allowing for concurrency.
They were concurrent to grammy language.
So basically in the mainstream
multi-threading was made popular by John.
It was too strong.
There were already a lot of programming
concurrent programming languages.
But they those programming languages were
designed basically to be concurrent. OK,
it was they were sort of confined in that
space in Java. Java was a.
A sort of C++ more say portable
programming language which included for
the first time threads.
And they got this idea,
which is very nice.
To tell you know what I create a class
and I represent as value of this class
and it is that are operating system and
it is that are threats.
OK.
To some extent those.
Values are not equivalent to any other
values, as it already happens with files.
Files are the same.
You got a number from the building system
and that's it. OK, so that was basically.
The history until the 90s and why it
happened in the 90s.
Not because in Java they were visionaries.
I mean they were visionaries in many ways,
but not for this.
It was because the operating system mid
90s in the threads in the libraries.
So there was a.
A clear use case to rely upon to get
better performance. Oh, by the way,
in the elements that we mentioned that
nobody recalled the.
Hyper threading,
which technically is not a form of
concurrency,
but it's an architecture inside our CPU
user that allows to to use.
Sort of two threads that execute
simultaneously on a single core.
It is not exactly true to some extent it
can be.
OK.
Uh.
OK, so let me zoom.
And let's discuss this.
So that was a typical way to obtain a a
thread in Java.
So you extends the class threads.
You override the run methods method.
And and then.
You know that the new newly created
thread will start executing this.
You know that multiple threads share the
process memory.
You know that you will have.
To introduce synchronization mechanisms
because.
Synchronization is a crucial process to
ensure of one.
Key element which is of aramount
imortance, which is.
That is the solution.
Why we use mutual exclusion?
What is the problem we are trying to
address?
Hmm.
Data.
I don't get the the word. Sorry,
can you speak louder?
Data. Uh.
Uh.
Problem are called race conditions. OK,
so that's the right the the the word was
there.
The problem is that the CPU implements
reading the memory and writing it to the
memory.
Not as an atomic operation.
You don't have instructions in the CPU to
ensure.
So basically you can read the value by
the way and you do a copy because inside
the CPU there are no references.
I mean we use references.
In in our programs,
but the CPU has no reference,
so the CPU is only able to copy data from
the memory to the register,
operate in the register right back and so
in this respect the.
The race condition is simply the
situation in which two threads reads the
same value.
You don't know the order of execution
because if that's executed independently
and and then they operate.
On the red version of the variable state
and eventually they may want to write the
updated value and without any form of
synchronization.
The risk is that operation on the on the
state may be.
Hands deleted because the first data is
successfully writes on on a memory
location.
Would keep going,
but the news there that the second trend
will write again, deleting the previous.
Then if that small register was your bank
account, you will.
You may be really happy or really unhappy
depending on the risk function.
OK, but basically that is the point.
And so synchronisation is a key a key
methods.
I know that you have studied all the
theory, PV and whatever in your curricula.
But basically,
once you reify the thread object,
so the thread that's operating system
element into a value in your programmer,
it is fairly natural to the same.
We synchronization mechanism.
You may have monitors, you may have.
Same of course,
and and and there have been a lot of
debate over the past on which is the the
best thing, by the way, of course.
With the evolution of the language,
you can implement an interface instead of
deriving from a thread from a class.
Same story.
Hey, everyone.
Now it's interesting.
I I didn't plan this,
but I think this is very,
very interesting.
Uh.
Because from interface, so inheritance,
both extents and implements are form of
inheritance because at the end of day run
as no implementation,
so it can be expressed as interface.
Uh,
now you have the option to pass a Lambda.
To the thread.
Which outlines and stress the fact one of
the big reasons because the functional
sub language has grown also in non
functional languages as Java was before.
It introduced to the lambdas because in
concurrent programming functions are
beautiful.
Functional programming switched very well.
Concordant programming. Why?
Why it is better than imperative
programming or even object oriented
programming?
That's the point.
So your colleague as as your colleague is
saying the reason why is that functions,
I mean in the purest form,
then of course if you have preference
asking.
Things that gets more complicated,
but in the purest form,
formal parameters are bound to values.
And so basically you copy the values into
the arguments,
you compute and you return a value which
is the result.
This means that there are basically no
memory contention in functional.
Programming.
At the same time,
you have much more copies operation
because of course you're making a copy of
the value, et cetera. So I mean,
but it allows the the the computing
programmer to decide where.
When to pay the cost of synchronization.
So this is one of the reasons because
functional programming has become really
important. OK.
Can you now generate an example with
synchronization?
Never an encounter.
So we got values of the count of the
counter class with in the increment which
allows you to write the increment the
internal counter and the accessor that
allows you to get the current count.
Is it?
No.
We have.
A counter object that is created.
The counter object is the.
Uh.
Used in this lambda.
The lambda is used to create.
The threats.
That's.
Yeah.
Then you start the threads. By the way,
when you start the thread,
of course the the current thread which is
a.
So every process when it started as a
main thread,
this main thread is is running this code
you.
With this line you start another a new
thread T1 and you keep going and so of
course you need also primitive for
waiting.
In this case,
join waits the end of the T1 and T2
thread.
OK.
So.
This version is bugged in the sense that
there is no coordination and so the risk
is that with the component execution some
increment will be lost.
Because when you do counter plus plus,
you're reading counter,
incrementing counter and dragging counter.
So there is some likeliness that the some
some increment will will be lost, OK.
So this will is incrementing the counter
by 10,000.
The result will be less than 20,
000 window threads.
This this is the resulting effect.
Now if you use a keyword in the language
that is called synchronized.
Passing the object,
but we are familiar with this.
Because if you remember the.
net implementation,
there is the sync block on top of any
objects in the runtime,
and the sync block has exactly this
purpose.
Serve the purpose of being an object that
you use to synchronize to acquire the
lock on that object.
And so basically this means.
If this is locked, wait,
wait for this to be unlocked,
otherwise acquire the locker and once you
get the locker.
Nobody else will be able to access this
block of code,
so I'm sure that I'm the only one that is
allowed to.
To execute.
Question the synchronized keyword.
How do you think is implemented?
What would be a question that makes sense
when you see a keyword like this?
First is is it the sugar or it is a
construct of the language?
Because we learn that sometimes
PROGRAMMING language the sugars syntax to
element or constituents of the
PROGRAMMING language not as a primitive.
So I would like to say OK,
is synchronized implemented as the sugars?
The.
Yes.
Yes and no, I will say.
So we're learning that the with respect
to the Java Virtual machine is not the
sugared.
I mean because there is no rewriting
system that rewrites in Java equivalent
synchronized.
But the JVM.
As monitors in the implementation and in
the by code you enter the monitor using
the object as a synchronization element
and you exit the monitor at the end.
Can you do?
A similar example in C shar with lock.
And show the C the sugaring.
I think it's interesting because in C#
they decided to be sugared properly.
So as you can see similar example of
course.
Very similar names and everything.
In C# we use lock as a constructor.
But actually lock is transformed in C#
itself.
And I think it's interesting because
basically.
It user steal the monitor implementation,
which is a an object in the standard
library.
And basically you use local variable to
know whether the lock has been taken or
not.
Because when you try to enter into a
monitor, typically you may wait,
but for instance you can specify a time
out.
I don't want wait more than 10
milliseconds and so in that case you may
exit without having the lock.
Then there is apparently at least in this,
but I I doubt that this is the full
implementation lock taken is only used
here but.
Uh.
No, sorry,
and it probably raises an exception in
case of unable to acquire the.
So the the code is correct.
Then you do the manipulation,
which is basically the code that you
wrote.
And it's interesting the finally you the
use of the finally constructs to ensure
that whether you get an exception or not,
if the lock and lock is has been taken,
if there has been an an exception in the
execution of a body.
In any under any condition,
if the locking is taken,
the monitor is released at the exit, OK.
Java implementation is compatible.
I mean it's just that in this case this
is implemented as a library in the
language rather than a primitive inside
the the.
The virtual machine. OK,
so now we starting looking at the basic
elements of control in C since Java,
basically threads represented inside the.
The PROGRAMMING language.
Um.
What are?
Drawbacks in using threads in your
applications.
In general,
I mean if I have a shared valuable,
I will need in any case that if I do some
concurrency execution,
I will have to synchronize anyway.
So yes,
but that is true also without threats,
if you have a any other form of
concurrency.
But why it's so uncomfortable to have
threats in an application?
So there are clearly.
Performance considerations.
Mm-hmm.
Creating a thread is not an easy
prediction.
On the scale of a process,
of course it's super fast,
but if you write a program that generates
threats,
that starts and stops and starts and
stops, the overhead is significant.
So, and this is clearly one problem,
but from a PROGRAMMING standpoint,
what do you think is the problem of
having threads?
Yes, debugging is very uncomfortable,
but in general you.
Modern debuggers allows you to suspend
the execution of the thread jumps from
one thread to the others.
Of course the debugging is complicated
because you will alter the timing of your
application if you set up a break point.
In in a particular part of your code,
because the the thread that is executing
that code was slow down to a point that
is basically unrealistic in the world in
the world will keep running. OK,
but apart from this, yes, debugging is 1.
So I will is that that is a philosophical
question.
And it's a subtle thing. So I mean,
I'm spending some time in trying to focus
your your mind on this subject so that
you can.
Appreciate because one may say OK,
but if underneath I got threads,
where's the point in having asynchronous
programs? I have threads,
which by the way are the primitives.
And so why at some point we felt the need
to move away from threats?
I'd say lazy,
lazy loading and lazy programming,
lazy loading and programming, I would say.
Threads brings you in the main syndrome.
I mean when you write a thread,
typically let me use the original version.
You write basically a main program.
You start thinking that your program is
confined inside that one,
and then you start looking for
communicating with other threats.
Through what? Through messages.
So suddenly you will start seeing it.
Synchronization mechanism with the
message passing it so that the thread can
safely send the events to another thread,
but.
If I have to define a computation by
slicing into the collaboration of threads,
even a simple algorithm may become super,
super,
super difficult to read for an example.
When you open a connection to a DB,
that is a huge operation in terms of a
programming language. It takes cycles.
You want to suspend it. OK,
so if you're using a thread,
you typically suspend the thread there,
so you have a blocked thread.
If I have a tag connections,
those are 10 blocker threats.
And you wait, you resume, you block again,
you resume.
So you're losing a lot of ability to go
concurrent. What is the alternative?
You start two threads, one for connection,
but then I have the problem that I I
can't.
Move on until I I have all the resources.
OK,
so threads are too system level to be
really useful in programming.
They are nice when you have you need a
background thread to.
Clean up your directory.
The thread starts,
execute and and stays there.
But when you want to use concurrency to
parallelize operation,
this is not the best possible options on
the table.
Mostly because it is difficult to write
code and to read code that is being
written that way.
Can you show me an example of a thread
pool?
Implementation in C# of.
Make it simple.
OK.
So we said there are basically.
Uh-2 reasons.
The first is uh uh the costs uh of
allocating and allocating threats.
Operating system don't support so many
threads per process. OK,
so if you write a a program which is for
each create thread,
you may easily put into a limit of the
operating system.
Second things we said is about.
Yeah.
Self-contained nature of the run method
which force you to write all your code
inside this main of the thread. OK,
let's first of all because I'm going in
the evolution timeline.
The first thing that happened,
it was the thread pool. OK,
thread pool is addressing basically the
first part of the problem.
Threats are expensive and you don't want
to allocate too many threats during your
programs.
So natural way to do I create a number of
threads.
When I need to start some background job,
I go to the thread pool for is there any
thread available? Yes or no? Yes.
OK this is can you please execute this
job?
For me.
Hmm.
So.
The code, as you can see,
immediately evolves because you're not
anymore thinking in terms of the run,
but I have a task which is in this code
is do work.
That should be defined somewhere. OK,
there we are. This is the work.
Uh.
So you pass the do work as a value,
so sort of Lambda technically is a
delegate if you remember delegates in the
runtime, OK.
And and and a number which allows you to
say, OK, I have 5 concurrent things going.
And you queue.
This means that it is not ensured that
all the five instances will receive a
dedicated threat if in the threat pool
you have three threats.
And you assign five work items,
then the first three will be executed as
soon as possible, starting a thread.
The other two will stay in queue waiting
for a thread available.
Q is working OK.
And this is the example.
Show me a minimal custom thread.
Pool implementation.
Because the full implementation of thread
pool,
I could go into the runtime and start
studying it,
but there are a lot of elements.
If you want to do an exercise,
please go into the Java virtual machine
or.
Uh.
net runtime and look for the thread pool
implementation.
It's a very nice exercise to understand
what's going on.
OK, so here we have a a very small.
This is a simple thread OOL.
So there is the cube.
Of the blocking collection actions,
which so it's a collection of action.
The action is is representing the work to
do.
So when you create a thread pool,
typically you can specify the worker
count.
Then thread pool implementation may have
different approaches.
Some may monitor the number of elements
in the queue and decide to allocate and
free threads.
Depending upon requests.
So for this reason I tell you it can be
interesting to read a real world
implementation that you you may find a
lot of considerations that are not
present here.
Then you create an array of threads.
Then you create a thread,
and a thread by definition needs to have
a a run, a run method. OK,
so there's no pause.
There's no pause that you can get from
the operating system of a thread. OK,
we need to provide basically a chunk of
code which is the body of the thread in
running the thread pool,
which basically will do always the same
thing.
Is there something in the queue? Yes. No.
If if there is a something in the queues,
pick the queue, run the action,
return the results, start again. OK,
so this is this is generated code.
So this is my expectation without having
read yet.
The code OK.
Of course we include also the name of the
of the of the threads so they're in
debugger and then you start the the the
thread.
So the thread starts and starts executing
the workload.
But.
So.
As you can see here,
there is a commenter which we welcome the
get consuming a new variable.
Blocks until work arrives.
Exit when complete adding is called. OK,
so I mean there is a specific object that
has been implemented in the library that
we we believe it works that way.
So I go into the queue and say OK get me.
Consuming enumerable which basically
blocks the thread until there is some
something in the queue. OK,
and in fact if you look at the queue is
of a a collection which is the blocking
collection.
Which is implemented the there is
internally a state, there is a monitor,
blah blah blah, synchronized, etcetera,
etcetera.
And it allows you basically to say, OK,
I need an element to consume as soon as
you have the the element to consume.
I will, uh, take on otherwise.
Wait, suspend. OK,
so this is a weight object.
Now as soon as I get a job,
the thread will receive the job in this
variable. It invokes the job.
It's a it's a type of action,
so it is like runnable in Java.
If there is a an exception job failed
just for the report,
of course in a real world implementation
it is not enough.
And this is the method which submit a new
job into the pool.
So you submit a job of type action if the
job is no complain,
otherwise you are to the queue.
The job.
And of course we are assuming that this
blocking here is synchronized because
it's clearly shared across multiple.
Multiple threads. OK, beware.
Here I'm basically granting, ensuring,
reassuring you that blocking collection
is synchronized, but please do check.
If this is holds true,
you want an example the Windows Forms
library.
Which has been fairly used for
implementing a lot of applications,
is not thread safe.
It is declared in the library
documentation that for efficiency reasons
they decide to say you need
synchronization,
do it your own synchronization.
I am not threat safe.
And in fact, if you start using threads,
if you use them in the wrong way,
you may get an exception from the library
that says call from different threads.
Sorry, I can't execute exception, OK.
So it is not obvious that all the we we
tried but the overhead of monitor
checking piles up and so when you are
implementing call libraries it is a
sensible choice sometimes to say OK this
is not synchronised.
So may even say OK if it's a different
random exception so that you can help the
programmer avoid tricks.
And so don't count that every class
library or class implementation is read
safe most of them.
Especially in the Uh code libraries are
not.
Dispose. OK, dispose.
Basically you you tell the the queue that
there are no items. So this basically.
We'll flush the queue and then you wait
every worker to complete the execution
and eventually you dispose everything. OK,
we said that disposer.
That is very similar to the finalizer in
Java.
You have no guarantee that is will be
invoked by the the garbage collector,
so you have no guarantees about the
timing, so sometimes.
In case like this,
you may want to explicitly invoke the
dispose to get rid of all the threats.
Otherwise you get it.
Have you ever had experienced some
application that you create and they stay
there?
Sometimes happens and the reason
typically is this one.
I mean you're waiting some thread that
has not been terminated properly. OK,
and here we have the the, the, the,
the demo usage of this.
So you create a thread pool with four
threads.
You submit four jobs.
Every job says least for 200 milliseconds,
right?
And that's it.
OK,
so thread pool is one of the abstractions.
Now things will be more interesting.
But to properly appreciate the.
The evolution you have to keep in mind
that the upcoming abstraction that I'm
about to introduce.
Are built on top of the thread pool. OK,
so at the end of the day,
the the real star of our show is the
thread pool.
But of course, we still have to address.
The uh.
If I survive to address the the second
part,
so the idea that sometimes I want to
express a computation as a whole.
This computation I know that will wait
for some resources that will take longer
to get. So I'd like to say, OK,
I want to suspend the execution there and
as soon as the execution.
Completes. OK.
So now I switch totally environmental.
Can you please show me?
An example.
Oh, uh, Jackson.
Uh.
Call the the original part then, please.
Oh,
learn that sometimes you you have in mind
that the original one and then oh Java
version and on 97 and 9000 has this new
feature feature.
OK, so uh, Jackson.
Thank you.
Ajax as a a nice you know who first
implemented Ajax.
We as the inventor objects.
Microsoft.
Basically, during the 90s I didn't spend.
Not even mentioning,
I may have before the end of the course
to have a quick run.
Maybe we will use it as an exercise to
recover that part because it's still
there. I mean you saw you know that in.
Uh, in Windows, uh,
have you ever seen that the Windows
registry?
Um.
Oh.
So this is a very old data structure.
It started before 95. It's still there.
Legacy undying.
You know that there are classes.
I'm pretty sure that eventually you ended
up editing this thing,
possibly collapsing your system at the
end of a session.
So.
Let me take.
So you may know that uh.
This is one of the core ways in which you
associate programs in into the witness
system.
OK.
So.
It does few attributes and then.
There is this key that say word document
12.
This is a reference to word.
What?
Documenter 12.
It's interesting because the registry is
basically a tree with cross references,
so at the end of the day is a graph. OK.
And oh, there is a class ID.
Which is.
Made by this beautiful,
globally unique identifier grid for
France.
You know what are these things and why
are there?
They are a standard introduced by
Microsoft.
Basically the problem was how can we get
a name which is very unlikely that
someone else will have in their lifetime.
So let's keep.
Natural language because humans have a
very poor fantasy,
so they it is very likely they will pick
up the same name twice.
So how can we be sure that that all the
developers in this world can get a unique
identifier that is very unlikely that
will collide with some others?
Uh, identifier.
And they come up with an algorithm that
has a high probability, not the certainty.
So there is still a chance that you can
get the very same GUID of another user.
And to be sure that the space was parsing
out,
you pick up a number which is 128 bit if
I'm right, which is 2 to the power of 128,
which is a huge space, so.
If you are good at randomize,
it is very unlikely that two GUIDs will
have the same value.
OK now all this thing because.
Let me copy this.
Let me annotate this.
It's interesting this class ID.
Plus ID.
There is a key in under classes. In fact,
in the original version Windows 95 where
these things have found life,
the purpose of the registry was this,
not the other keys.
Then they said OK, we got this.
Let's use also for system configuration,
but the the real purpose was programmable
programming. So class ID.
If I open the class ID you see that there
are a lot of.
This and if I look for F4.
F47 no F47 there we are 9B this one OK.
I find the name of an executable.
So this is the component object model.
It has been implemented around 9697 by
Microsoft as a binary component model in
which you can invoke functions of binary
components pre-compiled in different
languages.
So you have pointers to be tables to
interfaces and you can invoke functions
of processes or DLLS that are in process
in process.
There we are in process handler so.
This is this DLL will be responsible to
send the message to the external process
and this is how you can get Adobe Acrobat
inside or the vice versa.
That's that's basically the core
technology.
It's interesting because it's a component
model, OK.
I don't want to dig down more than this.
It's even beyond what I did expect,
but at least you have a clue of what was
going on. And this is the reason,
because if you go there and change some
of these,
you may destroy the graph and so the
system will start behaving.
Badly.
Um.
There are also type libraries,
which is basically the commutation of the
types in the in the components. OK,
so that thing was exposed inside Internet
Explorer.
So in Internet Explorer,
it was possible to I I forgot to finish
the phrases. Sorry,
because today I'm really struggling.
Firefox.
So how many of you are using Firefox?
The component model of Firefox is copied
from COM.
It's basically a different permutation of
COM. OK,
so you're using COM without domain.
Uh.
OK,
so Microsoft implemented the XML HTTP
request component for Office.
It wasn't meant for the web.
But Internet Explorer implementation was
using JavaScript that were was allowed to
start COM components including the XMLHTP
request and so.
That this thing became so popular that
eventually other browsers implemented the
XML HTTP request object inside the
browser,
not not more using not anymore using COM
because otherwise wouldn't be portable.
And this is how the web became
asynchronous. OK.
Hmm.
No.
OK.
So you create the HTTP request.
Then.
You open the request,
I'm jumping and then going back.
So this means I want to execute the HTTP
request using the verb GET.
On this URL which is in the same
directory in this example, so it's OK.
And then of course I'd like to say what
then you send the request.
I need to be called back when the data is
available.
And so.
They into exploiting the fact that
JavaScript is a functional programming
language.
They allow to register a call back
function that is invoked every time the
connection to the HTTP request that
change its state.
Typically I'm interested only in ready
state 4, which is OK done.
I'd like also to have an OK result,
so the resource is there 200.
And now I can copy the data that I get
through HTT inside my webpage.
This is the basics.
Of the Ajax technology, OK.
OK.
Looking for the clock.
I'm looking for a nice place to stop.
Now what is the problem is that if I
wanna make multiple?
Uh.
Can you generate an example?
In which?
You will form.
To get.
One after the other using.
Jacks.
If I'm lucky.
And the eye is helping me.
I hope to be able to.
Explain where's the point.
Thank you.
So now you see it's fairly easy.
I mean I have two files on on my web web
service.
I want to browse both of them and the
second I I need to read them in order.
And so first the 1st and then the 2nd and
with the Ajax this is the my only option
in the on ready state change.
I have to wait for the finish of the for
the end of the the first call.
And then I have to start again inside.
The result of the first request.
This leads to a code which is basically
unreadable.
It's not wrong,
it is simply unreadable because it's
structure is following this suspension
pattern and then pull back,
suspension pattern and then pull back.
OK.
Now if I'm a good programmer,
I can try to rewrite this code.
In a in a way in which I can see the real
actions,
trying to get rid of all these opens and
wait, etcetera, so that at least I know.
What comes first and then what comes
after?
You know what?
Concetually I'm writing read.
Risa fetch. Uh, sorry.
Batch.
Result one and then fetch.
Result 2.
This is what I'm basically writing, OK?
And you know what?
Functional programming allows me to have
a syntax that gives me the impression of
right of doing things in a sequence,
even though.
To the best of the knowledge,
I'm calling a function and inside someone
will call another function.
So I introduce, but we stop here.
I introduce the subject of Wednesday,
which is this style of decomposing a
computation.
By the means of writing some code and
then invoking a function which performs
some code and then may invoke another
function and so on.
It is known as continuation passing style
CPX.
And the continuation passive style is a
key element to really understand
JavaScript promises, C# passing, etcetera.
But at the core,
basically the idea is to try to retain
the functional structure of my function.
And the semantics,
even though I want to suspend and resume
and suspend again. And when I suspend,
I don't even care about if it's the same
thread.
I mean I want to execute this here.
I can suspend as soon as this thing
completes.
I can resume and even if a different
friend thread takes over,
for me it's fine.
It's OK because I I have only to compute
the computation until the end. OK,
this continuation passing style has
become the core.
Of the implement of the implementation of
asynchronous programming in programming
languages.
So on Wednesday we will start from here.
We will have some examples of
continuation passing style.
And then we'll look into JavaScript
promises,
I mean things that you may probably
already had and we will discuss also a
phase encountered and you we will also
discuss.
What are the implication in terms of
debugging?
Because debugging is an essential
activity,
so the ability to debug a program which
is execute,
I mean a single function is executed by
multiple threads as of course
implications in terms of the semantics of
the programming language.
There are a lot of lot of possible issues
there and honestly programming language
have been so good that now they preserve
the functional programming semantics even
though you are concurrent.
And this form of concurrency has become
dominant.
Threads are still used because you may
have to run a background task in your
application and a thread is a fundamental
element,
but for the core pattern of the executing
code which requires external.
Resources and you have to wait for those
resources and you don't want to be stuck
in while waiting for the resource.
Having otherwise an active wait group.
So I mean if you don't have suspension,
typically you have to wait explicitly.
So it's an active you're using CPU cycles.
Is there is there is there waiting then
the solution has become.
For almost everybody out there,
asynchronous programming and then we will
finish this part going back to the
modality computations, the F sharp.
Async implementation that I.
Exposed you too early in the course to be
able to discuss the the implementation,
which basically gives you an example of
how asynchronous combinations are in fact
a form of monadic computations.
They are properly modeled using this
thing.
So I thank you and see you on Wednesday.
you know